Civil Rights History Project collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Civil Rights History Project collection 2010-2016
AFC 2010/039
American Folklife Center
National Museum of African American History and Culture (U.S.)
1,202 items
1,024 video files (HD, Apple ProRes 4:2:2 HQ): color, sound
15 videocassettes (DVCam): color, sound; 1/4 in.
147 transcripts: digital, pdf
16 photographs: color, digital, jpg
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of 145 filmed oral history interviews of 175 participants in the United States civil rights movement and their family members.
Provenance
Accessioned; 2010-2016.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Other Repositories
The interviews in this collection are also a part of the collections of the National Museum of African American History and Culture.
Access and Restrictions
The Civil Rights History Project collection is open to research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Online Content
The Civil Rights History Project collection is available on the Library of Congress website at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/collafc.afc2010039.
The interviews are also accessible through the Library's YouTube site and the National Museum of African American History and Culture website.
Administrative History
On May 12, 2009, the U.S. Congress authorized a national initiative by passing The Civil Rights History Project Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-19). The law directed the Library of Congress (LOC) and the Smithsonian Institution's National Museum of African American History and Culture (NMAAHC) to conduct a survey of existing oral history collections with relevance to the civil rights movement, and to record new interviews with people who participated in the movement.
The American Folklore Society (AFS) oversaw a research team of four scholars who gathered information for the survey in 2010. The information was compiled into the CRHP National Survey Database of Civil Rights Collections in 2011 by Washington State University's Center for Digital Scholarship and Curation.
The NMAAHC sponsored six initial interviews in late 2010. The NMAAHC contracted with the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill's Southern Oral History Program to conduct 50 more interviews in 2011, recorded by Media Generation. An additional 52 interviews were conducted in 2013; and 37 interviews conducted in 2016. Videography and tech support was provided by the UNC Southern Oral History Program, Smithsonian Center for Folklife and Cultural Heritage, and Future View Inc.
Curation, preservation, and access to the interviews is a joint undertaking of the American Folklife Center and the NMAAHC.
Scope and Content
The collection contains 145 filmed oral history interviews of 175 participants in the United States civil rights movement and their family members. Also includes interview transcripts and photographs. The oral histories were conducted by historians Julian Bond, Taylor Branch, David P. Cline, Emilye Crosby, John Dittmer, Will Griffin, Hasan Kwame Jeffries, Joseph Mosnier, LaFleur Paysour, Dwandalyn Reece, Patricia Sullivan, and Kieran Walsh Taylor. Most of the interviews were filmed by John Bishop.
The interviews were conducted with activists who were also lawyers, judges, doctors, farmers, journalists, professors, union organizers, teachers, and musicians, among other occupations. The interviews cover a wide variety of topics within the civil rights movement, such as the influence of the labor movement, nonviolence and self-defense, religious faith, music, and the experiences of young activists. Most interviewees belonged to national organizations such as the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE), or the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). They also belonged to specialized and local groups including the Medical Committee for Human Rights (MCHR), the Deacons for Defense and Justice, the Cambridge (Maryland) Nonviolent Action Committee, Law Students Civil Rights Research Council (LSCRRC), the National Student Association (NSA), the Nonviolent Action Group (NAG), and the Newark Community Union Project. Some interviews were conducted in groups with families, couples, or participants of the same event. Several of the interviews were conducted with the children of civil rights leaders including Clara Luper, Robert Hicks, Gayle Jenkins, Ralph Abernathy and Oliver Hill, Sr. Interviews were also conducted with activists who worked in cities that are not well-known for their civil rights movement history, including Oklahoma City, Oklahoma; Saint Augustine, Florida; Seattle, Washington; and Bogalusa, Louisiana. Major civil rights movement events discussed in the interviews include the Albany Movement, the Selma to Montgomery Rights March, the Orangeburg Massacre, the March on Washington, the Freedom Rides, Mississippi Freedom Summer, the riots of 1968, and the murder of Emmett Till.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series: Series 1: Administrative; and Series 2: Interviews. Interviews are listed in order of interview number.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Abernathy, Donzaleigh; Abernathy, Juandalynn R.; Abernathy, Ralph David, 1959-; Abernathy, Ralph, 1926-1990.; Ackerman, David M.; Ackerman, Satoko Ito, 1939-; Adams-Johnson, Frankye; Alexander, Roberta; Anderson, Cynthia Baker; Anderson, Fletcher, 1938-; Anderson, William G., 1927-; Arellanes, Gloria, 1946-; Avery, Annie Pearl, 1943-; Bailey, D'Army, 1941-2015; Bassett, Emmett W., 1921-; Bassett, Priscilla, 1928-; Bates, Scott, 1923-2013; Becton, Julius W. (Julius Wesley), 1926-; Bennett, Geraldine Crawford; Bishop, John Melville; Blake, Harry, 1934-; Bond, Julian, 1940-2015; Booker, Simeon, 1918-2017; Branch, Raylawni G., 1941-; Branch, Taylor; Breaux, Toni, 1947-; Broadway, Louise W., 1930-; Brown, Amos C. (Amos Cleophilus); Brown, Harold K., 1934-; Brown, Robert J., 1935-; Browner, Clifford; Bruce, Walter, 1928-2014; Burns, Julia Matilda, 1938-; Burras, Carol Cummings, 1945-; Caldwell, Ben R.; Camarillo, Mateo, 1941-; Carawan, Candie; Carawan, Guy; Carlos, John, 1945-; Carter, Robert L., 1917-2012; Churchville, John Elliott; Clark, Robert George, 1929-; Cleaver, Kathleen; Cline, David P., 1969-; Collins, Barbara Maria, 1947-; Connor, Peggy Jean; Conway, Purcell Maurice, 1948-; Cotton, Dorothy F., 1930-2018; Cox, Courtland, 1941-; Crosby, David L., 1941-; Crosby, Emilye; Crosby, Patricia A.; Dahmer, Ellie J., 1925-; Dahmer, Vernon Ferdinand, 1908-1966.; Dahmer, Vernon, Jr.; Daniels, Jonathan Myrick, 1939-1965.; Derby, Doris Adelaide; Diamond, Dion T., 1941-; Dittmer, John, 1939-; Dixon, Aaron, 1949-; Dixon, Elmer; Dove, Samuel, 1942-; Dudley, John F., 1933-; Duncan, Gwendolyn Annette; Evers, Medgar Wiley, 1925-1963.; Finney, Ernest A., Jr. (Ernest Adolphus), 1931-2017; Forman, James, 1928-2005.; Fuller, Linda, 1941-; Funchess, Glenda, 1954-; Gaither, Thomas Walter, 1938-; Geiger, Jack, 1925-; George, Virginia Simms, 1940-; Glascoe, Myrtle Gonza; Greenberg, Jack, 1924-2016; Greene, Freddie, 1945-; Griffin, Willie James, 1974-; Grinage, Ben.; Grinnell, Gloria Claudette, 1939-; Guster, Leesco; Guyot, Lawrence, 1939-2012; Hamer, Fannie Lou.; Hamilton, Audrey Nell; Hansen, Bill, 1939-; Hayling, Robert Bagner; Head, Rosie M.; Henderson, Juadine; Hicks, Charles Ray, 1945-; Hicks, Darryl Robertson; Hicks, Gregory Vincent, 1950-; Hicks, Robert Lawrence, 1948-; Hicks, Robert, 1929-2010.; Hicks, Valeria Payton; Hicks, Valeria Payton.; Hildreth, Marilyn Luper, 1947-; Hildreth, Marilyn Luper, 1947-; Hill, Oliver W., 1949-; Holloway, Eddie A., 1952-; Holloway, Emma Kate; Holloway, Lucius, 1932-; Hopkins, Evans D., 1954-; Howard, Elbert, 1938-2018; Howell, Embry; Howell, Joseph T.; Hrabowski, Freeman A.; Huggins, Ericka; Hutchings, Phil, 1942-; Jackson, Gertrude Newsome, 1923-; Jarmon, Charles; Jeffries, Hasan Kwame, 1973-; Jenkins, Esau, 1910-1972.; Jenkins, Gayle, -2002.; Jenkins, Mary F., 1928-2014; Jenkins, Timothy Lionel, 1938-; Jenkins, Willie Elliot, 1952-; Jenkins, Willie Elliot, 1952-; Jones, Clarence B., 1931-; Jones, James Oscar, 1943-; Jones, Jamila, 1944-; Jones, Mary A., 1933-; Jones, Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1914-2018; Kennard, Clyde, 1927-1963.; King, Lonnie C., 1936-; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968.; Ladner, Dorie; Ladner, Joyce A.; Lawrence, William M., 1922-2014; Lawson, Jennifer, 1946-; Leventhal, Willy S. (Willy Siegel), 1946-2016; Long, Worth W.; Lowery, Joseph E.; Lucy, William, 1933-; Luper, Calvin, 1946-; Luper, Clara, 1923-2011.; Magee, Clarence; Mahone, Sam, 1945-; Marshall, Cecilia, 1928-; McCarty, Michael D., 1950-; McClary, Robert, 1938-2017; McCullar, Johnnie Ruth, 1940-; McDew, Charles; McKinney, Samuel Berry, 1926-; McLaurin, Charles; McNichols, Steven; Miller, Carolyn, 1953-; Miller, Grace H., 1932-; Miller, James E., 1949-; Moldovan, Alfred, 1921-2013; Montes, Carlos, 1947-; Moore, E. Maynard, 1938-; Moore, William Lewis, 1927-1963.; Mosnier, Joseph; Mtume, Norma; Mulholland, Joan Trumpauer, 1941-; Newson, Moses J., 1927-; Noonan, Martha P.; Parker, Wheeler, 1939-; Parker, Wheeler, 1939-; Patton, Gwendolyn M., 1943-; Paysour, LaFleur; Perry, Matthew J. (Matthew James), 1921-2011; Reece, Dwandalyn R.; Richardson, Gloria, 1922-; Richardson, Judy, 1944-; Robinson, Betty Garman; Robinson, Reginald, 1939-; Rosenberg, Jean Voelker; Rosenberg, John M., 1931-; Roxborough, Mildred Bond, 1926-; Russell, Bill, 1934-; Sales, Ruby; Saunders, William, 1935-; Seeger, Pete, 1919-2014; Sellers, Cleveland, 1944-; Sherrod, Charles, 1937-; Sherrod, Shirley, 1948-; Siler, Charles E.; Simmons, Gwendolyn Zoharah; Simpson, Euvester, 1945-; Smith, Jeanette, 1940-2018; Sobol, Anne Buxton; Sobol, Richard B.; Stewart, Eleanor, 1938-; Strickland, William, 1937-; Suggs, Frances L., 1935-; Suggs, Harold, 1935-; Sullivan, Patricia, 1950-; Taylor, Kieran Walsh; Terry, Esther M. A., 1939-; Thelwell, Michael; Till, Emmett, 1941-1955.; Till-Mobley, Mamie, 1921-2003.; Tillow, Kay; Tillow, Walter M., 1940-; Todd, Lisa Anderson, 1942-; Tuttle, Rick; Ulmer, JoeAnn Anderson; Varela, Maria, 1940-; Vickers, Barbara Edna, 1923-; Vivian, C. T.; Walker, Theresa Ann; Walker, Wyatt Tee; Walter, Mildred Pitts; Williams, Cecil J., 1937-; Williams, Junius W., 1943-; Wright, Simeon, 1942-2017; Wright, Simeon, 1942-2017.; Young, Carrie Lamar, 1948-; Young, Sam, 1950-; Zapata, Luis, 1944-2015; Zellner, Dorothy
Organizations
Albany Movement (Albany, Ga.); American Folklife Center; Archive of Folk Culture (Library of Congress); Black Panther Party.; Black People's Unity Movement (Philadelphia, Pa.); Bogalusa Voters League.; Cambridge Nonviolent Action Committee (Cambridge, Md.); Citizenship Education Program.; Civil Rights History Project (U.S.); Congress of Racial Equality.; Council of Federated Organizations (U.S.); Crown Zellerbach Corporation.; Deacons for Defense and Justice.; Democratic National Convention (1964: Atlantic City, N.J.); Dexter Avenue Baptist Church (Montgomery, Ala.); Federation of Southern Cooperatives.; Free Southern Theater.; Freedom Singers (SNCC); Harambee Singers.; Highlander Folk School (Monteagle, Tenn.); Koinonia Farm.; Law Students Civil Rights Research Council (U.S.); Lawyers Constitutional Defense Committee (U.S.); Library of Congress; March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom (1963: Washington, D.C.); Medical Committee for Human Rights (U.S.); Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party.; Mississippi Freedom Labor Union.; Mississippi Freedom Project.; Mississippi Freedom Schools.; Montgomery Gospel Trio.; N.S.M Freedom Library.; NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund.; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Youth Council.; National Brown Beret Organization.; National Museum of African American History and Culture (U.S.); Newark Community Union Project (N.J.); Nonviolent Action Group (Washington, D.C.); Northern Student Movement.; Selma to Montgomery Rights March (1965: Selma, Ala.); Southern Christian Leadership Conference.; Southern Oral History Program.; Southwest Georgia Project.; Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.); Summer Community Organization and Political Education (Organization); United States National Student Association.; United States. Department of Justice. Civil Rights Division--History.
Subjects
African American athletes--Interviews.; African American civil rights workers--Interviews.; African American clergy--Interviews.; African American college students--Interviews.; African American college teachers--Interviews.; African American journalists--Interviews.; African American judges--Interviews.; African American lawyers--Interviews.; African American veterans--Interviews.; African American women civil rights workers--Interviews.; Chicano movement.; Civil rights demonstrations--Florida--Saint Augustine.; Civil rights demonstrations--Louisiana--Bogalusa.; Civil rights demonstrations--Oklahoma--Oklahoma City.; Civil rights movements--United States.; Civil rights workers--United States--Interviews.; Discrimination in employment--United States.; Discrimination in medical care--United States.; Discrimination in public accommodations--United States.; Folk singers--Interviews.; Freedom Rides, 1961.; Montgomery Bus Boycott, Montgomery, Ala., 1955-1956.; Nonviolence--United States--History--20th century.; Poor People's Campaign.; School integration--United States.; Voter registration--Southern States.; Women civil rights workers--United States--Interviews.
Places
United States--Race relations.
Form/Genre
Digital photographs.; Interviews.; Manuscripts.; Oral histories.; Personal narratives.; Transcripts.; Video recordings.
Contents List
- Series 1: Administrative
  - Finding Aid (Box-folder 1/1)
- Series 2: Interviews
  - Robert L. Carter oral history interview conducted by Patricia Sullivan in New York, New York, October 23, 2010
    Biographical History: Robert L. Carter was born in 1917, grew up in New Jersey, and attended Lincoln University, Howard University Law School, and Columbia University Law School. He worked as a National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) attorney, legal assistant to Thurgood Marshall, 1944-1955, general counsel, 1955-1968 and judge, 1972-2012. He argued many civil rights cases such as Sweatt v. Painter, Brown v. Board of Education, and Sipuel v. Board of Regents of University of Oklahoma. Carter died in 2012.
    Summary: Robert L. Carter recalls growing up in Newark, New Jersey, and attending Lincoln University, Howard University Law School, and Columbia University. He discusses hearing Marian Anderson sing at the Lincoln Memorial and his service in the segregated army during World War II. He recounts his career as a lawyer with the NAACP Legal Defense Fund, including the Brown v. Board of Education case and other legal cases that ended segregation.
    - Moving Images, 3 videocassettes of 3 (DVCam) (186 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; afc2010039_crhp0001_mv01-03
    - Photographs, 2 photographs: digital, jpg files; afc2010039_crhp0001_ph1-2
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (87 pages); afc2010039_crhp0001_Carter_transcript (Box-folder 4/13)
  - Mildred Bond Roxborough oral history interview conducted by Julian Bond in New York, New York, October 29, 2010
    Biographical History: Mildred Bond Roxborough was born in 1926, grew up in Brownsville, Tennessee, and attended Howard University, New York University, and Columbia University. She married John W. Roxborough, II, in 1963. She worked as an administrator at the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) from 1954 to 1997.
    Summary: Roxborough discusses how she became active in the Civil Rights Movement at the age of nine, when she sold subscriptions to the NAACP The Crisis magazine. Roxborough began working with the NAACP as a fieldworker and worked in a variety of administrative positions including as director of development.
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (DVCam) (84 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; afc2010039_crhp0002_mv01-02
    - Photographs, 2 photographs: digital, jpg files; afc2010039_crhp0002_ph1-2
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (75 pages); afc2010039_crhp0002_Roxborough_transcript (Box-folder 4/14)
  - Myrtle Gonza Glascoe oral history interview conducted by Dwandalyn Reece in Capitol Heights, Maryland, November 17, 2010
    Biographical History: Myrtle Gonza Glascoe was born in 1936 and attended Howard University, University of Pennsylvania, and Harvard University. She worked as a social worker, college professor, and teacher. From 1965 to 1967 she was a Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) Field Secretary in Phillips County, Arkansas, and West Point, Mississippi.
    Summary: Myrtle Gonza Glascoe recalls growing up in Washington, D.C., attending Howard University and the University of Pennsylvania, and her early career in education and social work. She remembers joining the Baltimore Congress of Racial Equality (CORE), moving to California, and her work as a Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) Field Secretary in West Point, Mississippi and Phillips County, Arkansas, where she worked closely with Howard Himmelbaum and Gertrude Jackson. She also discusses her work as the director of the Avery Research Center and her opinions on the education of African Americans.
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (DVCam) (94 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; afc2010039_crhp0003_mv01-02
    - Photographs, 3 photographs: digital, jpg files; afc2010039_crhp0003_ph1-3
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (83 pages); afc2010039_crhp0003_Glascoe_transcript (Box-folder 4/15)
  - Gertrude Newsome Jackson oral history interview conducted by LaFleur Paysour in Marvell, Arkansas, November 22, 2010
    Biographical History: Gertrude Newsome Jackson was born in 1923 in Madison, Illinois, married Earliss Jackson in 1943, and had nine children. She attended Marvell High School and worked as a farmer and housewife. Jackson and her husband were farmers in Jonesridge, Arkansas, and provided food and shelter to Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) fieldworkers in Marvell, Arkansas during the 1960s.
    Summary: Gertrude Jackson recalls growing up in Madison, Illinois, and Marvell, Arkansas. She recalls organizing her community to renovate a local segregated school and becoming involved in the civil rights movement in rural Arkansas. She discusses assisting Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) fieldworkers Howard Himmelbaum and Myrtle Glascoe, working for Head Start, and starting a community center. Jackson's grandson is also interviewed.
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (DVCam) (117 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; afc2010039_crhp0004_mv01-02
    - Photographs, 3 photographs: digital, jpg files; afc2010039_crhp0004_ph1-3
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (102 pages); afc2010039_crhp0004_Jackson_transcript (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Lawrence Guyot oral history interview conducted by Julian Bond in Washington, D.C., December 30, 2010
    Biographical History: Lawrence Guyot, Jr., was born in 1939 in Pass Christian, Mississippi. He married Monica Kline in 1967 and had two children. He attended Tougaloo College and Rutgers University, worked as a lobbyist and longshoreman in Washington, D. C., and fundraiser for Mary Holmes Junior College. He was a Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) Field Secretary and chair of the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party. Guyot died in 2012.
    Summary: Lawrence Guyot recalls growing up in Pass Christian, Mississippi, and the influence of his family, and attending Tougaloo College. He remembers meeting members of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), joining the organization, and participating in Freedom Summer. He discusses his opinions and memories of Mississippi politics, the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, and his later life in Washington, D. C.
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (DVCam) (87 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; afc2010039_crhp0005_mv01-02
    - Photographs, 3 photographs: digital, jpg files; afc2010039_crhp0005_ph1-3
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (86 pages); afc2010039_crhp0005_Guyot_transcript (Box-folder 5/2)
  - C. T. Vivian oral history interview conducted by Taylor Branch in Atlanta, Georgia, March 29, 2011
    Biographical History: C. T. Vivian was born in 1924 in Howard County, Missouri, married Octavia Genes, and had four children. He attended Western Illinois University and worked as a minister and civil rights leader in Nashville, Tennessee.
    Summary: C. T. Vivian recalls growing up in Macomb, Illinois, working in Peoria, Illinois, and his call to the ministry. He discusses attending the American Baptist Theological Seminary in Nashville, Tennessee, where he met other civil rights activists and participated in demonstrations. He remembers planning the Freedom Rides, his imprisonment at Parchman Prison, the Children's Crusade in Birmingham, Alabama, and working for the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC).
    - Moving Images, 4 videocassettes of 4 (DVCam) (246 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; afc2010039_crhp0006_mv01-04
    - Photographs, 3 photographs: digital, jpg files; afc2010039_crhp0006_ph1-3
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (229 pages); afc2010039_crhp0006_Vivian_transcript (Box-folder 5/3-4)
  - Ruby Nell Sales oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Atlanta, Georgia, April 25, 2011
    Biographical History: Ruby Sales was born in 1948 and grew up in Alabama. She attended Carver High School, Tuskegee University, and Manhattanville College. She worked as the founder and director of Spirithouse and as a social justice activist. She was a Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) field worker in Alabama.
    Summary: Ruby Sales discusses her father's military career, growing up in Columbus, Georgia, and attending the Tuskegee Institute. She recalls joining the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), the Selma to Montgomery March, registering voters in Lowndes County, Alabama, and her arrest in Hayneville, Alabama. She remembers the murder of Jonathan Daniels, a seminary student who saved her life, and discusses her opinions on African American history and the current rate of African Americans in prison.
    - Moving Images, 10 video files of 10 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (92 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0007_mv01-10
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (46 pages); afc2010039_crhp0007_sales_transcript (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Doris Adelaide Derby oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Atlanta, Georgia, April 26, 2011
    Biographical History: Doris Derby was born in 1939 or 1940 in the Bronx, New York. She married Bob Banks and attended Hunter College and the University of Illinois. She worked as an artist, photographer and educator at Georgia State University. Derby was a civil rights activist and Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) fieldworker in Georgia.